{"tossups": [{"question": "This man appointed Michigan senator Zachariah Chandler to Secretary of the Interior in order to fight corruption within the Bureau of Indian Affairs. This man\u2019s Secretary of the Treasury, Benjamin Bristow, cracked down on a scandal during this president\u2019s tenure that culminated in the indictment of John McDonald and this president\u2019s private secretary, Orville Babcock. The Whiskey Ring scandal occurred during the presidency of, for ten points, what U.S. president and Civil War general who succeeded Andrew Johnson?", "answer": "Ulysses S. <b><u>Grant</u></b> (or Hiram Ulysses <b><u>Grant</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1791, the HMS <em>Pandora</em> broke on this geographical feature, killing 35 sailors. Discovered in 1768 by French explorer Louis de Bougainville, this geographic feature was the site of a major shipwreck for the HMS <em>Endeavour</em>, captained by James Cook, which was only able to break away due to a high tide. In 2018, the <em>National Geographic</em> said half of this place was dead, \u201cAkin to a forest after a devastating fire.\u201d For thousands of years, Torres Islanders and Aboriginal peoples have been using, for ten points, what coral system off the coast of Queensland, Australia?", "answer": "<b><u>Great Barrier Reef</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A composer from this musical era, Heinrich Biber [[BEE-buh]], called for strings to play <em>col legno</em> to evoke the sounds of battle in the opening of <em>Battalia</em>. Another composer from this era, who wrote the music for <em>The Bourgeois Gentleman</em>, died by stabbing himself with a conducting staff. The all-female ensemble of the Ospedale Della Pieta orphanage often sang music by a composer from this era who wrote four <em>concerti grossi</em> depicting changing weather throughout the year. For ten points, name this classical music era of Jean-Baptiste Lully, Antonio Vivaldi, and Johann Sebastian Bach.", "answer": "<b><u>Baroque</u></b> era", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Following the Bolshevik Revolution, an alternative version of this character was banned for being too \u201cbourgeois,\u201d with Joseph Stalin instead uplifting the Slavic \"Ded Moroz.\" Jerry Rubin mocked the House Un-American Activities Committee by holding a toy rifle while dressed as this character. Thomas Nast depicted this character draped with the American flag and holding a puppet that resembled Jefferson Davis. For ten points, what character, based on a historical saint, is known for giving presents to children during Christmas?", "answer": "<b><u>Santa</u></b> Claus (or <b><u>Kris Kringle</u></b>; accept <b><u>Saint Nic</u></b>holas; accept <b><u>Father Christmas</u> </b>before \u201cChristmas\u201d is mentioned; accept <b><u>Ded Moroz</u></b> before mentioned; accept regional equivalents for \u201cSanta Claus\u201d)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This author posited that \"Whatever is my right as a man is also the right of another\" in a response to Edmund Burke's <em>Reflections on the Revolution in France</em>, after which he was put on trial in absentia. This author described \"the summer soldier and the sunshine patriot\" who shrink from \"the times that try men's souls\" in <em>The American Crisis</em>. Before penning <em>Rights of Man</em>, this author asserted that the Colonies had plenty of resources to defeat Great Britain. For ten points, name this author who advocated for a \"republican government\" in <em>Common Sense</em>.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Paine</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A man in this profession, Dua-Kheti, may have written the work <em>The Satires of the</em> <em>Trades</em> which extolled the virtues of this occupation. A female recluse named Diemut who held this occupation is considered a local saint in her home region of Austria for single-handedly stocking the Wessobrunn [[VEH-soh-broohn]] Monastery library. This type of public servant developed the <em>demotic</em> Egyptian script for everyday use. Papyrus scrolls were used by, for ten points, which type of professional copyist who became obsolete after the invention of the printing press?", "answer": "<b><u>Scribe</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Calligrapher</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Copyist</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Writer\" or equivalents)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "NASA\u2019s future missions include launching the <em>Dragonfly</em> spacecraft to a feature of this celestial body to investigate its possible habitability. One of this planet\u2019s moons was determined to be habitable after the <em>Cassini</em> space probe found evidence of geysers. An anagram that describes a feature of this planet as a \u201cthin, flat ring\u201d was published by Christian Huygens [[HOY-gehns]] in 1655. In 1610, Galileo Galilei observed the extensive ring system of, for ten points, what gas giant, the second largest planet in the solar system?", "answer": "<b><u>Saturn</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This ruler formally ended imperial funding for the Neoplatonic Academy, which had been revived by Emperor Theodosius the Younger. In the text <em>The Buildings</em>, Procopius falsely attributes the construction of walls in Edessa and Tomis to this patron of his rather than to this man's uncle and predecessor of a similar name. The unpopularity of taxes raised by this monarch and his advisor, John the Cappadocian, led to the Nika [[NEE-kah]] Riots. The <em>Corpus Juris Civilis</em> was compiled by, for ten points, what sixth century Byzantine emperor who married Theodora?", "answer": "<b><u>Justinian</u></b> the Great (accept <b><u>Justinian</u></b> I; do not accept or prompt on \"Justin\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "To denounce the atrocities committed in this present-day country's war of independence, Archer Blood wrote a namesake telegram to the U.S. State Department. George Harrison and Ravi Shankar organized a benefit concert at Madison Square Garden in support of refugees in this country, which in 2013 witnessed the death of over eleven hundred people in the world's deadliest garment factory disaster. For ten points, name this densely populated country in South Asia which broke away from Pakistan in 1971.", "answer": "<b><u>Bangladesh</u></b> (or People's Republic of <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b>; or G\u00f4noprojatontr\u012b <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this war, future Stasi head Erich Mielke [[MEEL-kuh]] was a major participant in the killing of about 7000 priests during a \"red terror.\" During this war, Emilio Mola Vidal may have coined the term \"fifth column\" to refer to hidden supporters within a target territory. The Abraham Lincoln Brigades were composed of American volunteers who fought for the Republican side in this war, during which the Falangists allowed the Nazi Condor Legion to bomb Guernica. For ten points, name this 1930s war which ended with Francisco Franco establishing a fascist regime.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish Civil</u></b> War (or Guerra <b><u>Civil Espa\u00f1ola</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This author wrote a book subtitled <em>How I Got Licked</em> about his failed \"End Poverty in California\" campaign. This author stated, \"I was aiming for the public\u2019s heart, and by accident I hit it in the stomach\" after one of his novels led Congress to pass the Pure Food and Drug Act. That novel by this author concerned the Lithuanian immigrant Jurgus Rudkus, who works in Chicago's historic meatpacking industry. For ten points, name this activist and author of <em>The Jungle</em>.", "answer": "Upton <b><u>Sinclair</u></b> (or Upton Beall <b><u>Sinclair</u></b>, Jr.)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "A man from this province, who successfully argued to be made an exemplar of clemency, expressed wonder at wealthy Romans coveting \"poor huts.\" In this Roman province, Cartimandua [[kahr-tee-mahn-DOO-ah]] of the Brigantes [[bree-GAHN-tehs]] received and handed over the rebel leader Caratacus [[kah-rah-TAH-kooss]]. A generation later, Suetonius Paulinus put down a revolt in this region by defeating the Iceni [[\"eye\"-SEE-nee]] at Watling Street. For ten points, name this Roman province where Boudica's [[BOO-dih-kahs]] revolt occurred and of which the northern boundary was marked by Hadrian's Wall.", "answer": "<b><u>Britannia</u></b> (or Roman <b><u>Britain</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Great Britain,\" \"England,\" or \"United Kingdom\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This plan proposed simply amending the Articles of Confederation, which would represent the supreme law of the land. This plan, proposed by William Paterson, was opposed by Edmund Randolph and James Madison, whose Virginia Plan was worked, with elements of this plan, into the Connecticut Compromise. Calling for a unicameral legislature, for ten points, what was this plan proposing equal representation among all states?", "answer": "<b><u>New Jersey</u></b> Plan (or <b><u>Small State</u></b> Plan; accept <b><u>Paterson</u></b> Plan before \"Paterson\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man put the Lord Chamberlain in charge of theatre censorship after passing the Licensing Act. This man was a member of a social organization that met at Trumpet\u2019s Tavern known as the \u201cKit-Kat Club.\u201d News of the failed Battle of Cartagena [[car-tah-HEH-nah]] de Indias, which was part of the War of Jenkins' Ear, catalyzed the political downfall of this man. For ten points, identify this politician who came to power following the collapse of the South Sea Bubble and who is generally considered to be the first British prime minister.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Walpole</u></b>, <b><u>1st Earl of Orford</u></b> (accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A September 2021 report found that employees of this organization, which opened a 100 million dollar \"hub\" in Berlin, perpetrated sexual abuse in the Democratic Republic of the Congo during its 2018 to 2020 mission in that country. This organization's director-general, Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus [[ah-dah-NAHM geh-breh-YEH-sooss]] of Ethiopia, was accused of allowing China veto power over its report on the origins of the Covid-19 virus. For ten points, name this United Nations organ that oversees disease intervention and advocates for expanded medical care.", "answer": "<b><u>World Health Organization</u></b> (accept <b><u>WHO</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man starred in a series of commercials for Paul Masson [[mah-SOHN]] with the slogan \"We will sell no wine before its time.\" This man was infamously angered while recording a commercial for Findus frozen peas. In one film, a character played by this man erroneously states at the Vienna Riesenrad [[REE-zen-rahd]] that the Swiss had \"five hundred years of democracy and peace\" and produced only the cuckoo clock. For ten points, name this actor who portrayed Harry Lime in <em>The Third Man</em> and wrote and starred in <em>Citizen Kane</em>.", "answer": "Orson <b><u>Welles</u></b> (or George Orson <b><u>Welles</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This case's subject based his legal argument on precedents such as <em>Winny v.</em> <em>Whitesides</em> and <em>Rachel v. Walker</em>. The grocer Samuel Russell falsely testified that he hired the central person in this case. In this case, Chief Justice Taney [[TAW-nee]] stripped Congress of its power to ban slavery in the territories, nullifying the principle of \"once free, always free.\" For ten points, name this 1857 Supreme Court case which ruled that Black people in the United States lacked citizenship rights.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Dred Scott</u></b> v. John F.A. Sandford</em> (accept the <b><u>Dred Scott</u></b> case; accept Dred Scott v.  John F.A. <b><u>Sandford</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A group described by this color faced a six-day siege conducted by a volunteer army raised by by Toqto\u2019a. A leader of a group described by this color was a merchant who sold salt illegally before amassing a 10,000 man force and leading an attack on Taizhou; that man was Zhang Sicheng. A man who had, as a child, been sent to a Buddhist monastery near Haozhou joined that movement described by this color. That man, Zhou Yuanzhang, would later become the Hongwu Emperor. For ten points, a group described as wearing headgear of what color rebelled against the Yuan Dynasty?", "answer": "<b><u>red</u></b> (accept <b><u>H\u00f3ngs\u00e8</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man is often credited with saving one country's Jewish population by</u></b> <b><u>convincing Gustaf V of Sweden to open his borders to refugees. This man went by the</u></b> <b><u>pseudonym \u201cNicholas Baker\u201d while working as a consultant on the Manhattan</u></b> <b><u>Project. This scientist, with Ernest (+)</u> Rutherford, gives his name to an atomic model that exhibits electrons of a hydrogen atom moving in a (*) </b>\u201cplanetary\u201d motion. For ten points, what Danish scientist won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1922 for proposing that electrons orbit the nucleus in energy levels?", "answer": "Niels <b><u>Bohr</u></b> (or Niels Henrik David <b><u>Bohr</u></b>; accept <b><u>Bohr</u></b>-Rutherford Model)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this period, Ellen G. White developed the \"Great Controversy Theme\"</u></b> <b><u>which outlined the \"28 Fundamental Beliefs.\" In the 1830s, the second best-selling</u></b> <b><u>book in the U.S. after the Bible was an autobiography by a figure in this movement,</u></b> <b><u>Lorenzo Dow. (+)</u> During this movement, radical sects of Christianity arose such as the (*) </b>Shakers and the Latter-Day Saints. For ten points, name this early 19th century period of religious revival in the U.S. which led to an increase in membership for Baptists and Methodists.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Great Awakening</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; prompt on \"Nineteenth Century\" or \"1800s\"; do not accept \"First Great Awakening\")", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>A historical fairy-tale opera in this language depicts one sister promising to</u></b> <b><u>bear a \"bogatyr\" knight for a certain monarch. That opera in this language partially</u></b> <b><u>takes place in the principality of Tmutarakan [[tuh-MOO-tah-RAH-kahn]]. The</u></b> <b><u>monologue \"I have attained supreme power\" (+)</u> is sung by the title character of an opera in this language who gives the throne to his son. That play in this language takes place during the Time (*) </b>of Troubles. For ten points, give this language of operas such as <em>The Tale of Tsar Saltan</em> and <em>Boris Godunov</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Russian</u></b> (or <b><u>Russkiy</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man attacked Mary I and stated that female monarchs went against</u></b> <b><u>biblical teachings in the pamphlet</u> </b><em><b><u>The First Blast of the Trumpet Against the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Monstrous Regiment of Women</u></b></em><b><u>. This man briefly preached to a group of Marian exiles</u></b> <b><u>in Frankfurt and claimed that (+)</u> Charles V was \"no less enemy to Christ than was Nero.\" In Stirling, this man gave the sermon at James VI's [[the Sixth's]] (*) </b>coronation.  For ten points, name this Scottish Calvinist theologian and founder of Presbyterianism.", "answer": "John <b><u>Knox</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country resettled Jewish refugees from Nazi Germany in the town of</u></b> <b><u>Sos\u00faa [[soh-SOO-ah]] after the \u00c9vian Conference. During one massacre in this</u></b> <b><u>country, the fate of the victims was determined by how they pronounced the term</u></b> <b><u>\"perejil'' [[peh-reh-HEEL]] (+)</u> when soldiers held up a certain herb. One leader of this country had several thousands migrants from a neighboring country killed in the Parsley Massacre and was nicknamed \"El (*) </b>Jefe\" [[HE-feh]]. For ten points, name this Caribbean country that was ruled for over thirty years by Rafael Trujillo [[troo-HEE-yoh]] from Santo Domingo.", "answer": "<b><u>Dominican Republic</u></b> (or <b><u>Rep\u00fablica Dominicana</u></b>; prompt on \"DR\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Dominica\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The Defence No. I</u></b></em><b><u> calls the \u201cspirit\u201d of these entities \u201can inseparable appendage</u></b> <b><u>of human nature.\" Another essay argues that rather than removing the causes of</u></b> <b><u>these entities, we should control their effects. The power of these entities is curbed</u></b> <b><u>by Republicanism (+)</u> according to \"Federalist X [[\"TEN\"]].\" George Washington called the \u201calternating domination\u201d of these entities \u201ca frightful despotism\u201d in his (*) </b>farewell address. For ten points, name these organizations that coordinate political candidates and have included the Federalists and Democrats.", "answer": "Political <b><u>Parties</u></b> (accept <b><u>Faction</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>A ceramic mask from the Sesklo culture depicted these creatures as early as</u></b> <b><u>6000 BCE. The oldest stone pediment in Greece displays an image of one of these</u></b> <b><u>creatures at the temple of Corfu. According to Hesiod\u2019s</u> </b><em><b><u>Theogony</u></b></em><b><u>, (+)</u> Ceto and Phorcys were the parents of these creatures, which were often depicted beheaded (*) </b>and placed onto shields, like the Aegis. Believed by the Ancient Greeks to have provided protective magic for homes, for ten points, what mythological serpent-headed monsters included Medusa?", "answer": "<b><u>Gorgon</u></b>s (or <b><u>Gorgon</u></b> sisters; prompt on \"Medusa(s)\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This organization built the largest wooden ship of the late 16th century,</u></b> <b><u>known as</u> </b><em><b><u>Der Grosse Adler</u></b></em><b><u> for service during the Northern Seven Years' War. The</u></b> <em><b><u>Stalhof</u></b></em><b><u> of London served as the principal</u> </b><em><b><u>kontor</u></b></em><b><u>, (+)</u> or foreign trading post, of this organization until Edward IV expelled a group of Cologne merchants. Maritime trade of the medieval Baltic (*) </b>and North Seas was dominated by, for ten points, what trade league of German and Scandinavian guilds and towns?", "answer": "<b><u>Hanseatic</u></b> League (accept D\u00fcdesche <b><u>Hanse</u></b>; accept <b><u>Hanze</u></b>; accept <b><u>Hansa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this empire, unfree persons known as</u> </b><em><b><u>siraku</u></b></em><b><u> were tied to temple lands and</u></b> <b><u>acted as tenants for the local religion. The capture of the Medean Wall following the</u></b> <b><u>539 BC Battle of Opis led to the collapse of this empire. The Chaldean (+)</u> period of this empire began after the chieftain Nabopolassar took advantage of the weakness of the Neo-Assyrians to dominate (*) </b>Mesopotamia. The likes of Nebuchadnezzar and Hammurabi led iterations of, for ten points, what empire centered on a namesake city in which the Hanging Gardens were built?", "answer": "<b><u>Babylon</u></b>ia (accept <b><u>Babylon</u></b>ian Empire; accept Neo-<b><u>Babylon</u></b>ian Empire)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}